A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, F-L FA392
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, F-L
1911-1992
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller Foundation
FA392
51.11 Cubic Feet Boxes 137-273
Actual extent is unknown.
Biographical/Historical note
Rockefeller Foundation diaries:
Officers of the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and its staff members in the field often visited educational, scientific and research institutions and laboratories in many parts of the world to maintain contacts and assess work being done. Officers and field staff frequently conferred with government officials regarding the operation of the RF's programs. In order to preserve accurate records for the guidance of other RF officers, those who carried on these activities kept diaries of their day-to-day contacts and impressions. These diaries were sent to the RF office, where they circulated among officers and staff to the extent deemed advisable.
Rockefeller Foundation:
The Rockefeller Foundation was established by act of the New York State Legislature approved by the Governor on May 14, 1913, "to promote the well-being of mankind throughout the world." Between 1913 and 1928 the China Medical Board, the International Health Board, and the Division of Medical Education functioned as divisions of the Foundation, concentrating on the administration of programs in public health and medical education. A Division of Studies was created in 1923 to handle projects outside the medical field. These early years were experimental as the new foundation studied the methods of philanthropy and explored its relationships with other Rockefeller boards.
Although the Rockefeller Foundation is the largest and best known philanthropy founded by the Rockefeller family, it was neither the first nor the last to be established. The Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (1901), the General Education Board (1902), the Rockefeller Sanitary Commission for the Eradication of Hookworm Disease (1909), and the Bureau of Social Hygiene (1911) all existed earlier. When the Foundation was created, the Sanitary Commission was disbanded. After the establishment of the Foundation, the Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial (1918) and the International Education Board (1923) were created.
The Rockefeller boards and their programs were reconsidered and reorganized in 1927-1928 in order to avoid overlapping programs. The International Health Board of the Foundation was disbanded and an International Health Division was organized. The China Medical Board, Inc., was established as a separately incorporated institution, and the China Medical Board of the Foundation ceased to exist. The Division of Studies was dropped and the Division of Medical Education was phased out. The Laura Spelman Rockefeller Memorial was combined with the Foundation and the Spelman Fund of New York was chartered to continue activities of the LSRM that were not absorbed by the Foundation. The International Education Board was disbanded.
As a result of this reorganization, the Foundation adopted a program which included public health work (administered by the IHD), the advancement of knowledge in the medical and natural sciences (in part taken over from the IEB), the social sciences (formerly the field of the LSRM), and the humanities and arts (shared with the GEB). The Rockefeller Institute and the Bureau of Social Hygiene were not affected by the reorganization. The program adopted by the Foundation at this time remained basically the same for the next twenty years.
As its files accumulated, the Foundation maintained a card index recording the names of institutional and individual grantees and correspondents. A microfilm copy of this index is available at the Archive Center.
File Plan note
RG 12
Organization of the Foundation's archives:
RG 1 Projects
RG 2 General Correspondence
RG 3 Administration, Program and Policy
RG 4 China Medical Board
RG 5 International Health Board/Division
RG 6 Field Offices
RG 7 Treasurer's Office
RG 8 Comptroller
RG 9 Personnel
RG 10 Fellowships
RG 11 Information Services
RG 12 Diaries
RG 13 Oral Histories
RG 14 Counsel
RG 15 Secretary
RG 16 Minutes and Officers Actions
RG 17 Dockets
RG 18 Declinations (100F)
RG 19 Non-textual Materials
RG 20 Communications Office
Scope and Contents note
Rockefeller Foundation officers' diaries:
Diaries are of two types: regular daily diaries, and special trip diaries. Some diaries have indexes, which are bound in the annual volume; indexing was not a requirement but was left to the discretion of the officers, and not all diaries are indexed.
Diaries frequently contain information given in confidence, and were thus treated as confidential., The period covered is approximately 1911-1992.
Other Finding Aids note
Other available finding aids describing Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries include:
FA391 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries A-E.
FA393 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries M-R.
FA394 Rockefeller Foundation records, Officers' Diaries S-Z.
Conditions Governing Access note
Officers' diaries are open for scholarly research provided that (1) the diarist is deceased and (2) the volume to be examined is at least twenty years old. All reasonable efforts will be made to determine the fate of the diarist(s), but if such efforts are fruitless then the material will remain closed to scholarly research until 100 years after the officer's year of birth.
Arrangement
Alphabetically by surname.
Philanthropy -- United States; Life sciences; Humanities; Medical sciences; Public health; Race and society; Diseases; Epidemics; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations; Charities; African Americans; Arts; Philanthropy
- Fahs, Charles B.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
  The archival material has been reformatted. Access to the original archival material is restricted. Digital files and user copies of the microfilm are available for scholarly access.
  Biographical / Historical
  Charles Burton Fahs was born in Brooklyn, New York on September 8, 1908. His parents, Sophia (Sophie) Lyon Fahs and Charles Harvey Fahs, who went by Harvey, raised Burton and his sisters Dorothy, Ruth (who died in childhood), and Lois in Brooklyn, New Jersey, and California. Harvey traveled a great deal for his job and was often absent from the family home, leaving Sophie to raise the children on her own. The Fahs parents encouraged exploration and independent thinking among their children and were a very close-knit family, despite Harvey's lengthy absences.
  Following the Fahs family tradition, Burton attended Northwestern University in Evanston, Illinois for his undergraduate study, majoring in political science. He also displayed a keen interest for international studies and comparative politics, and he pursued these interests in class as well as in his extracurricular activities, primarily through his membership in the Institute for Oriental Students. Here he met many international students, engaged in discussions and debates over current events, and began to explore diverse cultures through the life experiences of other students.
  Burton completed his undergraduate studies in 1929 and traveled to Europe for the summer. During the 1929-1930 school year, he attended the University of Berlin and enriched his language skills. Burton also attended a variety of German student political meetings, furthering his interest in current events and political systems.
  For the 1930-1931 school year, Burton returned to Northwestern to begin his graduate studies. Burton met Jamie Ross sometime during this period, and they became engaged in 1931 after Burton completed his master's thesis and exams. Jamie had been raised in Colorado Springs, Colorado and had come to Northwestern for a master's degree in Classics. She remained in Evanston after the completion of her degree and worked as a Latin instructor during the couple's courtship and early marriage. Burton and Jamie were married in Colorado Springs, Colorado on June 27, 1932.
  Burton continued his studies during the early years of their marriage, receiving his PhD in 1933 and embarking on three years of study in Japanese language, culture, and politics, first in Paris and then in Kyoto and Tokyo. Jamie traveled with her husband during these years, and the two lived frugally but comfortably on Burton's fellowship stipend. During the year in Paris, Burton and Jamie met Edwin O. Reischauer, a lifelong friend and the American Ambassador to Japan during Burton's employment at the U.S. Embassy in Tokyo. In 1935, their son James Harvey Fahs was born in Kyoto.
  In 1937, the Fahs family returned to the United States and Burton began his academic career as an instructor, and later an assistant professor, at Pomona College in Claremont, California. The family planned for an eighteen month sabbatical in Japan and China for 1940-1941, but their plans abruptly changed with the imminent threat of war. After arriving in Japan, it was decided that Jamie and Jimmie should return to the U.S. while Burton would continue on to China, where he stayed for several months before rejoining his family in California.
  Burton took a leave of absence from Pomona and joined the Office of Strategic Services in the fall of 1941. The family relocated to the Washington, D.C. area, where daughter Barbara Ruth was born in 1943. Burton remained with OSS for the duration of the war, eventually being promoted to Chief of the Research and Analysis Division (Far East). Between October 1944 and February 1945, Burton traveled to China, Burma, and India to assess various overseas research units.
  At the conclusion of World War II, Burton resigned from Pomona College. Within a year, he also resigned from the Department of State (where the Research and Analysis Division had been transferred at the conclusion of the war) to accept a position with the Rockefeller Foundation as Assistant Director in the Humanities Division. In 1950, Burton was appointed Director of the Humanities Division. The Fahs family lived in Fair Lawn, New Jersey during this period. Jamie was elected to the local school board and became involved in Girl Scouts. Burton traveled a great deal for his job with the Rockefeller Foundation, often visiting other parts of the U.S. or foreign countries for 4-6 week periods.
  In 1961, Burton resigned from the Rockefeller Foundation. By 1962, he was appointed Minister-Counselor for Cultural and Public Affairs in the Embassy of the United States in Tokyo, Japan. This appointment was unique and created specifically to match Burton's educational background and talents. The intervention of friends like Dean Rusk and Edwin Reischauer smoothed the way for the creation of this position. Burton and Jamie returned to Tokyo, and both were extremely busy with diplomatic duties and the attendant expectations and social obligations which accompany such a position. During this time, both of their children married; Barbara had her ceremony in Tokyo.
  Burton remained with the Embassy in Tokyo until 1967, and once again the Fahses returned to the United States. Burton accepted a one year academic position as Harry C. Trexler Distinguished Visiting Professor at Muhlenberg College in Allentown, Pennsylvania. The following year, Burton was appointed Director of International Studies at Miami University in Miami, Ohio. He and Jamie moved to Oxford, Ohio and settled into a new home. Jamie returned to academic life as well, tutoring students in Latin.
  Burton and Jamie retired from Miami University in 1973, traveling internationally in their retirement and spending time with their growing family. Burton continued his work with Grolier, Inc. during this time, beginning a project to publish a set of encyclopedias in Japanese. This project would ultimately be abandoned.
  Beginning in 1975, Burton experienced serious health problems related to terminal illness. He kept his illness at bay for several years, but his health began to fail significantly in late 1979. It was also this year that marks the presentation of two significant awards, an honorary degree from Miami University and the Japan Foundation Award. Despite his declining health, special arrangements were made so that Burton could travel to Japan to accept this award. Jamie, Jim, and Barbara accompanied him for this momentous occasion.
  Charles Burton Fahs died on February 26, 1980 at the age of 71. A memorial service was held at the Sesquicentennial Chapel at Miami University on March 1, and Burton's ashes were interred in the Oxford Cemetery on August 24 of the same year.
  Japan; East Asia
  - 1946 August 4-1947 April 7, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Rockefeller Foundation; 236 pages (Reel M Fah 1, Frame 1, Box 137)
    Scope and Contents note
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs as the Assistant Director of the Humanities Division of the RF discusses projects and proposals with professionals. He is involved in the progress of Humanities programs, selection of fellows and grants-in-aid, and development of new research. The Humanities Division vision is to extend an international understanding of methods in humanistic study, and assist in training and research of foreign cultures. Fahs surveys various American universities to observe their Far East programs. The Chinese History Project is detailed and he attends various conferences.
    Korea; Japan; United States; Diaries; Asia; China; Humanities; Education
  - 1947 April 8-May 23, Rockefeller Foundation; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 165 pages (Reel M Fah 1, Frame 237, Box 137)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs as the Assistant Director of the Humanities Division of the RF discusses projects and proposals with professionals. He is involved in the progress of Humanities programs, selection of fellows and grants-in-aid, and development of new research. The Humanities Division vision is to extend an international understanding of methods in humanistic study, and assist in training and research of foreign cultures. Fahs surveys various Asian universities and libraries. Notes on Coronado Beach Conference of the Institute of Pacific Relations are included as well as "Trip to the Far East (8 April-14 July 1947)" diary.
    China; Diaries; Education; Japan; United States; Humanities; Philippines
  - 1947 July 29-December 29, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 140 pages (Box 137, Reel M Fah 1, Frame 402)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs as the Assistant Director of the Humanities Division of the RF discusses projects and proposals with professionals. He is involved in the progress of Humanities programs, selection of fellows and grants-in-aid, and development of new research. The Humanities Division vision is to extend an international understanding of methods in humanistic study, and assist in training and research of foreign cultures. Fahs gives general impressions on the American Historical Association, attends meetings and conferences.
    Diaries; United States; Humanities; Education
  - 1948 January 2-April 3, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 133 pages (Box 137, Reel M Fah 1, Frame 600)
    General note
    This frame number is unconfirmed.
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grants- in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought. Fahs surveys university programs, attends conferences and discusses plans for an African studies program.
    Africa; Diaries; United States; Linguistics; Humanities; Education
  - Trip to the Far East, 1948 April 6-July 16; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 156 pages (Reel M Fah 1, Frame 832, Box 137)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grants-in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought. Fahs surveys and tours university facilities, programs and staff.
    China; Education; East Asia; Humanities; Hong Kong; Korea; Japan; Canada; Diaries; Libraries; Philippines; United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
  - 1948 July 23-December 31, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 182 pages (Reel M Fah 1, Frame 1,014, Box 137)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grants-in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought. The diary details the American Council of Learned Sciences (ACLS) translation project.
    Diaries; United States; Universities and colleges -- United States; Humanities; Libraries; East Asia; Education
  - Trip to India, the Far East, and Europe - Index, 1949 January 3-April 9; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Box 137, Reel M Fah 1, Frame 1,023)
    Index Trip to India, Far East and Europe; 9 pages.
    Europe; Asia; India; indexes (reference sources)
  - Trip to India, the Far East, and Europe, 1949 January 3-April 9; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 161 pages (Box 138, Reel M Fah 1, Frame 1,025)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grants-in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought. The diary details the American Council of Learned Sciences (ACLS) translation project. Fahs tours and surveys various institutions in his trip to India, Far East and Europe. He assesses their programs, research and staff.
    Universities and colleges -- United States; Denmark; Sweden; Thailand; United States; Philippines; Singapore; Diaries; Libraries; Linguistics; Education; England; East Asia; India; Java; France; Humanities
  - 1949 April 11-June 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 119 pages (Box 138, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought.
    East Asia; Education; United States; Universities and colleges -- United States; Humanities; Libraries; Diaries; Linguistics; Slavic studies
  - Trip to Mexico, 1949 July 2-September 2; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 73 pages (Box 138, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 71)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought. Fahs take a trip to Mexico.
    Linguistics; Libraries; Humanities; Education; Universities and colleges -- United States; United States; Slavic studies; Mexico; Diaries; East Asia
  - 1949 September 7-December 30, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 158 pages (Box 138, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 193)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goal is the realization of humanistic studies and the arts can make to contemporary life and thought. Fahs attends the Conference of Americanists, Conference on Southern Asia Studies, National Conference on the Occupied Countries and the First Meeting of the Fulbright Fellowship Selection Committee.
    Universities and colleges -- United States; Diaries; Humanities; Education; East Asia; United States; Slavic studies; Linguistics; Libraries
  - 1950 January 2-April 11, Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 180 pages (Box 138, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 351)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goals are the study of language, intercultural understanding and general humanities projects.
    East Asia; Education; Linguistics; Slavic studies; Humanities; Diaries; Libraries; United States; Universities and colleges -- United States
  - Trip to the Far East - Index, 1950 April 12-June 18; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton) (Box 138, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 531)
    Index Trip to the Far East; 12 April-18June 1950; 15 pages.
    indexes (reference sources)
  - Trip to the Far East, 1950 April 12-June 18; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); 134 pages (Box 138, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 546)
    Organized according to interview and visit, Fahs discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of humanities. He is involved in the progress of Humanities Division programs, selection of fellows and grant in-aid, and development of new research. The Division's goals are the study of language, intercultural understanding and general humanities projects. Fahs tours the Far East and visits various libraries.
    Methodology; Korea; Japan; Linguistics; Libraries; Humanities; Indonesia; Encyclopedias and dictionaries; Hong Kong; Diaries; East Asia; Education; Bibliography; Universities and colleges -- United States; Thailand
  - 1950 June 19-September 28, Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; 108 pages (Reel M Fah 2, Frame 682, Box 138)
    Libraries; Linguistics; Methodology; United States; Universities and colleges -- United States; Diaries; Bibliography; Education; East Asia; Humanities; Encyclopedias and dictionaries
  - Trip to Latin America - Index, 1950 September 30-November 5; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton); Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities. (Reel M Fah 2, Frame 790, Box 139)
    Index Trip to Latin America; 30 September-5 November 1950; 10 pages.
  - Trip to Latin America, 1950 September 30-November 5; Rockefeller Foundation. Division of Humanities.; Fahs, Charles B. (Charles Burton) (Box 139, Reel M Fah 2, Frame 800)